CHAPTER 2. The Pool of Tears “Curiouser and curiouser!” cried Alice (she
was so much surprised, that for the moment she quite forgot how to speak
good English); “now I’m opening out like the largest telescope that ever was
goodbye feet!” (for when she looked down at her feet, they seemed to be almost out of
sight, they were getting so far off). “Oh, my poor little feet, I wonder who will put
on your shoes and stockings for you now, dears? I’m sure I should be able! I shall
be a great deal too far off to trouble myself about you: you must manage the
best way you can;— ;—but I must be kind to them,” thought Alice, “or maybe they won’t
walk the way I want to Let me see: I’ll
give them a new pair of boots every Christmas.” And she went on planning to
herself how she would manage it.
“They must go by the carrier,” she thought; “and how funny it’ll seem, sending
presents to one’s own feet! And how odd the directions will look! Alice’s Right
Foot Esquire heartthrog near the Fender, with Alice’s love Oh dear, what nonsense
I’m talking!” Just then her head struck against the roof of the hall: in fact she
was now more than nine feet high, and she at once took up the little golden key
and hurried off to the garden door.
Poor Alice! It was as much as she could do, lying down on one side, to look
through into the garden with one eye; but to get through was more hopeless than ever:
she sat down and began to cry again. “You ought to be ashamed of yourself,” said
Alice, “a great girl like you,” (she might well say this), “to go on crying in this
way! Stop this moment, I tell you!” But she went on all the same, shedding gallons of
tears, until there was a large pool all around her, about four inches deep and
reaching half down the hall. After a time she heard a little pattering of feet in
the distance, and she hastily dried her eyes to see what was coming. It was the
White Rabbit returning, splendidly dressed, with a pair of white kid gloves
in one hand and a large fan in the other: he came trotting along in a great hurry,
muttering to himself as he came, “Oh! the Duchess, the Duchess! Oh! won’t she be
savage if I kept her waiting!” Alice felt so desperate that she was ready to ask
help of anyone so, when the Rabbit came near her, she began, in a low, timid voice
uh If you please, sir—” The Rabbit started violently, dropped the
white kid gloves and the fan, and scurried away into the darkness as hard
as he could go. Alice took up the fan and
gloves, and, as the hall was very hot, she kept fanning herself all the time she
went on talking: “Dear, dear! How queer everything is today And yesterday things
went on just as usual. I wonder if I’ve been changed in the night? Let me think:
was I the same when I got up this morning?
I almost think I can remember feeling a little different.
But if I’m not the same, the next question is, Who in the world am I?
Ah, that’s the great puzzle!” And she began thinking over all the children she knew
that were of the same age as herself, to see if she could have been changed for
any of them.
“I’m sure I’m not Ada,” she said, “for her
hair goes in such long ringlets, and mine doesn’t go in ringlets at all; and I’m
sure I can’t be Mabel, for I know all sorts of things, and she, oh! she knows
such a very little!
Besides, she’s she, and I’m I, and— —oh dear, how puzzling it all is!
I’ll try if I know all the things I used to know.
Let me see: four times five is twelve, and four times six is thirteen, and four
times seven is— —oh dear! I shall never get to 20 at that rate!
However, the Multiplication Table doesn’t signify: let’s try Geography. London is
the capital of Paris, and Paris is the capital of Rome, and Rome— —no, that’s all wrong,
I’m certain!
I must have been changed for Mabel!
I’ll try and say How goth the little and she crossed her hands on her lap as
if she were saying lessons, and began to repeat it, but her voice sounded hoarse
and strange, and the words did not come the same as they used to
How doth the little crocodile Improve his shining tale And pour the waters of
the Nile On every golden scale!
“How cheerfully he seems to grin, How neatly spread his claws, And welcome
little fishes in With gently smiling jaws oh I’m sure those are not the right
words,” said poor Alice, and her eyes filled with tears again as she went on, “I
must be Mabel after all, and I shall have to go on and live in that pokey little
house, and have next and no toys to play with, and oh! ever so many lessons to learn!
No, I’ve made up my mind about it; if I’m
Mabel, I’ll stay down here! It’ll be no use they're putting their heads down and
saying ‘Come up again, dear!’ I shall only look up and say ‘Who am I then? Tell me
first, and then, if I like being that person, I’ll come up: if not, I’ll stay
down here till I’m somebody else’— ’—but, oh dear!” cried Alice, with a sudden
burst of tears, “I do wish they would put their heads down I'm so very tired of
being all alone here!” As she said this she looked down at her hands, and was
surprised to see that she had put on one of the Rabbit’s little white kid gloves
while she was talking.
“How can I have done that?” she thought oh I must be growing small again.”
She got up and went to the table to measure herself by it, and found that, as
nearly as she could guess, she was now about two feet high, and was going on
shrinking rapidly: she soon found out that the cause of this was the fan she
was holding, and she dropped it hastily, just in time to avoid shrinking away all
together That was a narrow escape!” said Alice, a good deal frightened at the
sudden change, but very glad to find herself still in existence; “and now for the garden!”
and she ran with all speed back to the little door:
but, alas! the little door was shut again, and the little golden key was lying on
the glass table as before, “and things are worse than ever,” thought
the poor child fry never was so small as this before, never! And I declare it’s too
bad, that it is!” As she said these words her foot slipped,
and in another moment, splash! she was up to her chin in salt water. Her first idea
was that she had somehow fallen into the sea, “and in that case I can go back by
railway,” she said to herself. (Alice had been to the seaside once in her life, and
had come to the general conclusion, that wherever you go to on the English coast
you find a number of bathing machines in the sea, some children digging in the
sand with wooden spades, then a row of lodging houses, and behind them a railway station.)
However, she soon made out that she was in the pool of tears which she had wept
when she was nine feet high wish I hadn’t cried so much!” said Alice,
as she swam about, trying to find her way out. “I shall be punished for it now, I
suppose, by being drowned in my own tears!
That will be a queer thing, to be sure!
However, everything is queer today Just then she heard something splashing about
in the pool a little way off, and she swam nearer to make out what it was:
at first she thought it must be a walrus or a hippopotamus, but then she
remembered how small she was now, and she soon made out that it was only a mouse
that had slipped in like herself.
“Would it be of any use, now,” thought Alice, “to speak to this mouse?
Everything is so out of the way down here, that I should think very likely it
can talk: at any rate, there’s no harm in trying.” So she began
oh Mouse, do you know the way out of this pool I'm very tired of swimming about
here oh Mouse!” (Alice thought this must be the right way
of speaking to a mouse: she had never done such a thing before, but she
remembered having seen in her brother’s Latin Grammar, “A mouse— —of a mouse— —to a
mouse— —a mouse a mouse!”) The Mouse looked at her rather
inquisitively, and seemed to her to wink with one of its little eyes, but it said nothing.
“Perhaps it doesn’t understand English,” thought Alice; “I dare say it’s a French
mouse, come over with William the Conqueror.” (For, with all her knowledge of history,
Alice had no very clear notion how long ago anything had happened.)
So she began again
which was the first sentence in her French lesson book The Mouse gave a
sudden leap out of the water, and seemed to quiver all over with fright. “Oh, I beg
your pardon cry to Alice hastily, afraid that she had hurt the poor animals
feelings. “I quite forgot you don't like cats.” “Not like cats!” cried the Mouse, in a
shrill, passionate voice. “Would you like cats if you were me?” “Well,
perhaps not,” said Alice in a soothing tone: “don’t be angry about it. And yet I
wish I could show you our cat Dinah: I
think you’d take a fancy to cats if you
could only see her. She is such a dear quiet thing,” Alice went on, half to
herself, as she swam lazily about in the pool, “and she sits purring so nicely by
the fire, licking her paws and washing her face— —and she is such a nice soft
thing to nurse— —and she’s such a capital one for catching mice— —oh, I beg your
pardon!” cried Alice again, for this time the Mouse was bristling all over, and she
felt certain it must be really offended.
“We won’t talk about her anymore if you’d rather not.” “We indeed!” cried the Mouse, who
was trembling down to the end of his tail. “As if I would talk on such a
subject! Our family always hated cats: nasty, low, vulgar things! Don’t let me
hear the name again!” “I won’t indeed!” said Alice, in a great hurry to change the
subject of conversation. “Are you— —are you fond— —of— —of dogs?”
The Mouse did not answer, so Alice went on eagerly: “There is such a nice little
dog near our house I should like to show you! A little bright-eyed terrier, you
know, with oh, such long curly brown hair!
And it’ll fetch things when you throw them, and it’ll sit up and beg for its
dinner, and all sorts of things— —I can’t remember half of them— —and it belongs to
a farmer, you know, and he says it’s so useful, it’s worth a hundred pounds! He
says it kills all the rats and— —oh dear!” cried Alice in a sorrowful tone, “I’m
afraid I’ve offended it again!” For the Mouse was swimming away from her as hard
as it could go, and making quite a commotion in the pool as it went.
So she called softly after it, “Mouse deer Do come back again, and we won’t talk
about cats or dogs either, if you don’t like them!” When the Mouse heard this, it turned
round and swam slowly back to her: its face was quite pale (with passion, Alice
thought), and it said in a low trembling voice,
“Let us get to the shore, and I’ll tell you my history, and you’ll understand why
it is I hate cats and dogs.” It was high time to go, for the pool was
getting quite crowded with the birds and animals that had fallen into it:
there were a Duck and a Dodo, a lorry and an Eaglet, and several other curious creatures.
Alice led the way, and the whole party swam to the shore